Uh, I didn't put that fourth picture
there. And it it looks a little
disrespectful. I don't know.
But I don't know where the sunglasses.
You put the sunglasses
on.
Uh, anyway,
uh, I was on Pabonar on the left and
yeah, that's better.
[Music]
Uh and he's a so the thing is those of
you in staircase house uh you can say
pabongache he was the great master of
lam rim he wrote the the greatest lam
rim and uh his disciple chimpache in the
middle did all the work he's the roa and
the
anatal for pabona okay and you need that
you need people like that. So he spent
many years of his life
uh helping to print and and prepare his
teachers teachings. Okay. And uh Pabong
Pache is famous for Bajay Yogini. He
wrote the best commentary about Bajay
Yogini. I translated it. Um I've never
published those translations. I have
three or four I have about I think it's
about 20 or 30,000 pages of Diamond Way
translations. Uh but we you you
shouldn't uh normally publish them. You
you should give them to your student.
Okay. So it's waiting for you. All
right. There's
about there's about 20,000 pages
something like that. And I worked hard
on it. I worked for 10 years on it. and
uh his book is the greatest. His diamond
way book is the greatest. We will study
his book. Okay. So you should know the
lineage that you are. If people ask you
what's your lineage now coolest
thing and then I think then we'll switch
over to the angel for today.
Uh let me see what I got out of. No,
we'll keep
going. Poor angel always gets short
changed.
uh
uh in the in in my monastery
ceremony there's uh 12 great houses.
Okay, you got five, they got 12. And
uh there are 12 great houses
for over 500 years. Okay. And
uh my teacher is from Geron House. Okay.
Say gerum.
So uh at Princeton there used to be a
sort of a house custom from your home
state. So I'm from Arizona. When I went
to
Princeton, we we meet with all the other
kids from Arizona and you know, we do
naughty things
together and uh and it was really fun
and it was really dear, you know, and we
got very close to each other and because
we're in a foreign part of another
state, we don't know all these people.
They live they're from the
armpit. We're from Arizona. We don't
have any. It's very difficult to be
friends with them. They have they're New
York New York people. They want to know
about kafi and and uh we're like it's
difficult to be their friends. So you
you have a house from your own state and
uh in the same thing in the monastery.
Okay. So people travel sometimes
thousands of miles to come to study at
the great three
monasteries and uh there's a house for
gerong. Gerong means east east Tibet
near like Changdu area. Okay. They have
their own dialect. They have their own
language and um so
uh but other people can go there. If
you're from Arizona and you're the first
uh white guy in uh in how many years?
600 years. Then there's no Arizona
house. So they say you can join uh Ghon
House because my teacher was from Geron
House. And what I want to say is why
Geron House is the best
house is that uh Pabon Rimp came from
our house. Okay. Uh the greatest teacher
uh is uh Pabonich. So my teacher and and
Pabon came from Gon House. When your
teacher come from Gearon House, you are
part of Gillon House. Okay. So you are
Gong house. All right. You're also
whatever house you are staircase
whatever but uh you should have some you
should be happy that you are part of
Girong house and you can brag about it.
You know people say what house you
connected to. You can say girong and
they say what's gong and say it's just
the greatest writer in history. Uh
pabunker but he uh was reborn. He passed
away in 1941 I think.
And he was
reborn and that reborn llama uh finished
his gish and then suddenly he died. Uh
and then he was reborn again. And uh so
the young Pabrace was my
classmate and uh we had many good I I
examined him for his gishi. I was the
number one examiner and uh it was cool.
and he's a great teacher now. He's he
teaches uh all over the world. He's a
good teacher. Okay. Uh these are in the
beginning of
the steps of the path. In the beginning
of diamond way to prepare for diamond
way we have to learn our teachers and
these are your teachers. Okay? And and
I'll tell you something. I don't care
what country they came from. you know, I
I'm not loyal to a particular country.
You know, I'm not to be honest, uh I'm
not attracted to a lot of Tibetan uh
culture. It's not something I'm
interested in. You know, there's if I
give you
the shall I sing uh
Tibetan, it's very similar to Beijing
opera. Okay.
And then I'm
like then uh there's many things about
you know I'm not attached to uh American
culture. I'm I'm probably the least
American American you ever met. And uh
I'm not attached to a particular country
or particular culture. I I'm not trying
to sell Tibet or China or Japan or, you
know, I just feel like we're all one
country, Russia. I I I feel uh that's
how I feel about it. So, I'm not trying
to make you Tibetan or I'm not trying to
sell you Chinese things or you It's
a It's a way of thinking. It's a way of
living your life. And there's people
in every country who follow it and
there's people in every country who
don't follow it. All the ones who follow
it are in the same country. You see what
I mean? They're in L rim country. Okay?
And I that's how I see it. I that's just
the way I see it. Okay? So, I'm not
trying to I'm not trying to make you
Tibetan. I'm not trying to get you to
wear this strange
hat. You know, ask me how many times I
wore my hat in Rimrock.
How did I
know? Like I never wore it once, you
know, cuz it's not appropriate. It's not
appropriate to wear it around Phoenix,
Arizona or something. You know, I wore
it my robes once in New York and um this
guy stopped me and he said, "Oh, you
what are you goddamn Moses?" You know,
I'm like, "Peace, man. Peace." You know,
and
So I don't think it's so important uh
that what you wear or or if you have a
bell or you know I I don't think it's
personally I don't think it's so
important. Okay. I think we you
you dress to fit the people you're
teaching. If you teach business people
you got that
picture. If you're going to a business
talk the one with the four
teachers. If you're going to a business
talk, you go in a nice car and you wear
a nice suit. Okay? Really? Seriously.
And then uh if you when you're in
Diamond Mountain, you just wear your
your normal clothes. And uh that's lam
rim. Okay? That's lam rim. So I'm not
trying to sell something cultural to
you. Buddhism is not a culture. Buddhism
is a way of thinking. Diamond way is a
way of thinking. Okay?
Uh so in this in this text so far we are
bowing down to the teachers and I wanted
to show a person bowing down
successfully. Next
picture. Uh
yeah. So uh I mean uh our company
exploded. Our our company doubled every
18 months in we're the fastest growing
company in the history of New York. Why?
Just by accident.
And uh so I was desperate for workers,
you know, and I put out the word, if
anyone knows anyone who knows jewelry,
if they they know some jewelry skills,
please let me know. And we were working
like crazy hours. I I was working till 2
every night. And uh and then uh I I had
I hired a lady from Barbados and then
she's like seven feet tall and uh she
said, "I know somebody." And I'm like,
"Okay, tell them to come in." Uh two
people came in. Uh one was Uma
Thurman. Uh she came in, she needed a
job. She didn't get famous. She didn't
get into the movies yet.
And then uh I interviewed her and I
said, "Listen," I said, "Do you really
want to be a secretary in a diamond
company?" And she said, "No." And I
said, "Well, what do you really want to
do?" And she says, "I want to be an
actress." And I said, "I'll tell you
what. You I'm not going to hire you and
and you go be an actress." Okay. And
then I think two months later, she got
the role in the Dangerous Lang,
something like that. And then she became
she's been on Vogue cover more than any
other woman. Uh her father always thanks
me uh for not hiring her. And uh at the
same time this short black Barbados lady
came in and I interviewed her and uh she
said she had some jewelry skills and
then I said uh one thing our company is
tough you know we got to work till 1:00
2:00. I mean we're a crazy company and
so if I hire you you're going to have to
work when I tell you to work. and she
says, "I don't do
that." And I'm like, you know, I'm very
very busy. I'm in a huge company and
here's this lady come in and say, "I
don't do that." So I'm like, "Well, why
did you come here?" And she said, "I
need job, you know, but I don't do
that." And I said, "What do you do?" And
she says, "I work when I want to work."
And I'm like, I just looked at her, you
know, and I looked at her friend who
brought her uh and I'm
like, you
know, and then I this word yes came out
of my
mouth and I was like, what? You know,
and uh so I hired her and she was
trouble and uh you know, but she she
grew up in the company. Then she she
became a a great diamond jewelry master.
She became she handled the largest
account which was $20 million account
something. And uh she became really good
at it, you know. And then
uh I don't know uh I was sleeping in New
York once a week cuz I have to open the
vaults. Somebody has to open the vaults.
Only three people are allowed to to know
the secret numbers, you know. So, I come
in once a week. I sleep in New York. And
then I started teaching people in my
hotel room on the bed because there's no
place else. I sit on the desk and they
sit on the bed. And then it got more and
more people and they're all trying to
sit on the bed. And she heard about it
and she said, "Can I come to your class
someday?" I'm like, "You won't like it."
And she's like, "No, let me try." you
know, and then she came and then she
really liked it and then she studied,
studied, studied and then she became a
nun. My teacher made her a nun and she
she and I started
ACI together. Okay. And
uh that was how long
ago? 30 years ago. Okay. And uh then she
came out to Diamond Mountain. She did a
three-year retreat uh and she helped
build this place. She built this we
built this temple by our hands. All the
students carry the bricks and build the
place. It was hard and she's in such a
she never saw anyone change so much. She
was very difficult
person. No. And then she become this
extremely happy person. and extreme and
then uh then we did a we had a chance to
do a second threeyear retreat and she's
like I'm up for it and she's the only
person here right John I think who did
two she did six years of deep retreat
uh so pretty amazing people don't
know she had cancer the whole time she
had cancer when I met her and uh people
didn't know and we didn't tell anybody
body. But uh she
had bad cancer and she just keep going,
you know, and uh so
uh finally she passed away and
uh but you know people always
uh doing all these nice prostrations,
you know, blah blah. And I think uh if
you want to uh prostrate to the
llamas like pick up a shovel, you know,
and build a tempo, you know, you know,
do
something do something to help, you
know, that's all nice. You know, all
these people hand me red
envelope, you know, and they're like,
"Oh, we love you." And I'm like, "Yeah,
I got a shovel." Yeah, I don't do that.
So
uh I think uh when you prostrate you
know and uh when you bow to the lineage
uh think about this kind of prostration
okay and it's just hard work you know to
to build this place just hard work okay
20 years of hard work those stupid
Chinese young people they're like oh
we're doing the same thing I'm like
yeah my wife I asked my wife, should I
let them try? And she's like,
"Yeah, let them try." Because it's hard.
It's really hard. It It makes you uh
strong. Okay. If if you want to
prostrate to the llamas, if you want to
honor the llamas, then clean the toilet
or, you know, do something like that.
That's the real
uh frustration. It's not
this. Those are easy. Those things are
easy. Okay. Hard work. If you want to
honor the lineage, then hard work. Okay.
Uh I'm going to do a little more and
then I'm going to take
Q&A. Okay. Especially about Diamond Way,
but anything you want. Okay. So, I'll do
about I'll stop in about 15 minutes and
we'll do Q&A. Okay.
uh you should have some questions about
how you continue with your diamond
weight practice and things like that.
Okay. Okay. Last thing uh there's
a there's an unusual part of the of
Gibson's book
uh where uh they talk about if you study
lom rim uh you get
eyes. Okay. And that's the next picture.
Uh yeah, this is a famous stupa. I think
it's
Bodhinat in Nepal in Katadu. And I think
this is some people say it's where Lord
Buddha was born. Uh but uh it's an
unusual stupa. It's famous because it
has these strange eyes on it, you know,
and then it's Buddha's eyes. It's part
of a huge huge stupa. And uh when we
finished this stupa, Dr. Woo told me
those are kind of mini stups, aren't
they? And I'm like, what do you mean?
And it these are pure marble. You you
can't, you know, it's like pure diamond.
It's like you can't. He's like, well, I
was kind of thinking of boden art, you
know, which is like five stories high.
I'm
like, we also have, by the way, we have
to respect
the the uh view. We can't ruin the
desert. We we don't feel like we can uh
put big Buddhist statues and stuff like
that. They have to fit into the
mountain. We don't want to hurt the
mountain and we want to make the stupas
quiet and elegant. Okay. So anyway, uh
eyes are very important and and somebody
said to
Tonkaba, if you study Lamri, you get the
eyes to see the world, to really see the
world. And he got
upset. And he said, that's not what the
book says. That's not what it says. And
then they said, what do you mean? And he
said, the L rim is the
ice. Okay. Not that you study lam rim
and you get eyes. Not like that. He said
lam rim is the eyes. If you learn lam
rim, you have the ice. Okay, got it.
What? for seeing messages. Okay. In
diamond
way l and by the way
uh the uh the author chi chony llama
right he said sonapa said he told the
story about sonapa and sonapa's eyes and
then I checked it
in John Brady's database. I checked it
and I found it. Uh, and it's at the it's
on the last page of the lrimm chiml.
It's it's uh 1,000 pages into the lrim
chiml and uh it it talks about the eyes.
Lom rim is eyes and if you have lam rim
you have eyes and if you don't have lom
rim you don't have eyes.
Okay. What's it mean for us?
Uh there's a very very famous
uh very very famous quotation from Lord
Buddha and somebody asked
him which meditation posture is
better and he's like what do you mean
and there's this big fight for 2,000
years. Do you put your left hand down
first or do you put your right hand down
first and do you cross your right leg
first or do you cross your left leg
first? Big fight. Okay, there's a big
fight you know. So somebody asked him
what position what's your meditation
what's your favorite meditation
position? And he said I have
three. Lord Buddha said I have three.
you know, and they said, "What?" And he
said, "I meditate when I'm flat on my
bed. I meditate when I sit in a chair.
And I meditate when I stand up. That's
all." Okay? And uh so I wanted to give
you a proposal.
Uh so
classically Lord Buddha said there's
three times you can focus on your
meditation when you're a Buddha is
whether you're laying down, sitting or
standing up. Okay, which is you know all
the time. Don't think there's any other
choice. Word probably could come up with
something flying
or Yeah. Oh, no. I would count that as
standing up personally. Um but anyway,
uh I propose that until we meet again in
Mexico
City, whether you're online in Mexico
City or whether you come to Mexico City,
I
propose that uh we have a sort of
a that we all try to
uh when we're walking, when we're
traveling somewhere, when we're going
somewhere, in a car or walking, okay?
When you're going somewhere,
uh especially walking in a street in
Shenzhen with your son or flying
somewhere or in a car. Okay. When you
are moving to go somewhere. Got it. Uh
walking, traveling in a car, flying in
an airplane. Okay. when you're I I would
like to make a
deal among all of our we're now a small
Diamond Way group,
right? Including the online guys. Uh
until Mexico City, which is July 18th,
right? For four days. Uh until then,
when you travel, let's make a deal that
you look for messages.
Okay. And you know, you can sleep on
your bed. You don't have to look for
messages. And you can sit at your
breakfast table. You don't have to look
for messages. But I
propose that we all
agree to look for messages when we're
traveling in a car or on a plane or
walking to a city. Okay. That's all.
Okay. Agree. Agree. That was three
people, I think.
Okay. Okay. All right. Cool. So,
remember, you know, what's your
homework? Somebody asked you, "What's
your diamond way homework?" It's when
I'm traveling,
uh, I'm supposed to see if there's any
messages that were sent to me. Okay? And
I get a lot of messages on airplanes.
I'm on airplanes a lot. I keep my ears
open. You know, somebody gives me a
message. I remember one lady was
uh looking at her cell phone the whole
way like it's a how many hours to
Japan? 11 hours you know and I think
about 10 hours she was like this you
know and I'm I'm kind of
like irritated. I don't know why I'm
just irritated. somebody would look at
their phone the whole way to Japan, you
know, and uh then I kind of was curious
what someone could look at for 11
hours. And uh I looked, you know, I you
when you go to the toilet, you spy on
people and I went to the toilet and I'm
like, I just want to see what website
she's looking at. And um that's when I
found out you can turn the camera around
and look at
yourself, you know. Hi Jesse, Michael.
And uh she was checking her makeup for
hours, you know, and I I was like, "Wow,
she's checking her makeup for 11 hours,
you know. I'm such a better
person, you know. I don't even know how
to do that." And uh that makes me a
better person. I would
never just think about myself for 11
hours, you know, and then suddenly I'm
like it's a message. She's telling me I
think about myself 11 hours out of 11
hours, you know. And maybe she's
Vajioini. Maybe she's an angel. Maybe
she's a Buddha. Maybe she's a lady
Buddha, you know. Maybe she's trying to
get me to get this. Maybe if I would
just figure it out, she could go to
sleep, but she has to sit there for 11
hours. That guy's so stupid. He didn't
get it. Keep trying.
[Laughter]
Okay. So, uh, watch from that's our
homework. Okay, that's what I'd like to
do together as a group, as a team. Uh we
when you're traveling then uh look for
messages. Okay. And they can be unusual.
They can be really strange. You know
what's a message when a scorpion crawls
on your
foot during
tree? You'll never forget
tree. Okay. What's the what's the
message? Okay. We're looking for
messages. And if and if I have to tell
you what's the greatest diamond way
practice, it's looking for messages. I
think it's one of the greatest. Okay.
All right.
And is it a message? Was she sending me
a message? Was she a Buddha sending me a
message?
I can't say she was, but I can't say she
wasn't. I can't say I know she was. But
I can't say I I know she wasn't. And
that state of doubt between I can't say
she was. I can't say I know she was and
I can't say I know she wasn't. That
middle place uh of doubt is extremely
powerful karma. Okay? If it's one of the
most powerful karmas there is. If you
want financial freedom, if you want to
throw $100 bills at people all day, or
you want to be happy or you want to have
the greatest wife in the world or
husband,
uh, this is the karma. It's an extremely
powerful karma, okay? Everything you
ever dreamed of will will come. Okay?
It's very unusual. It's very strange.
Okay? Got it? That doubt is is the is
one of the most powerful karmas there
is. Okay? And and it will produce weird
things like very very successful life,
very happy life, okay? And it's so
cheap. It doesn't cost anything to be
paranoid about the
lady, you know. It doesn't cost you
anything. It's no effort at all. It
takes like 10 seconds, you know, on the
way to the toilet. Huh? Another message.
Hi. Bye. You know, do your
toilet. I could tell you about
No, no. We had an interesting flight
from
China. Speaking of toilets,
but I'm not going to make fun of my
friend who was throwing up and diarrhea
at the same time. And they the airplane
company closed the toilet.
Uh anyway, buddy, it's a good way to
lose weight.
Uh okay, let's do Q&A. Okay, you got
your homework, right? We all I have my
homework. Okay. All right. And we'll do
we'll finish Angel de Devil sometime
soon.
Tim, you who's going to choose the Tim?
did choose or somebody
choose. By the way, after class, I got
to go quick. Okay. I'm I'm u there's a a
lab waiting for me. Okay. So, Gala,
thank you so much for the class. So, I'm
just wondering what is the message for
us that we are here in the class and we
see the scorpion like
uh and I'll say something about that.
Okay.
Um I think message messages are tailor
made. It means I think messages are sent
to you personally. So I think it's uh
part of this
practice is it's not that gel decides
the message, you decide the message
because because I don't know your life.
I don't know what's going on in your
life. You know I have many many
students. I don't know what's happening
in their lives. you know, you know
what's happening in your life. So, um,
one thing about messages is they are
created by the Buddhas to fit you
personally. Okay? And two people can get
different messages from the same event.
Okay? Two two people can get different
messages from the scorpion, you know,
and and they're both true. Even if
they're opposite, they're both true.
Okay? And that's the cool thing about
messages. So they are one thing about
diamond way is that all this stuff is
happening was designed for you
personally. It's a personal message for
you from the Buddha. Okay? And you can
take it and you can use it. And that's
that's diamond way. That is diamond way.
You asked me to teach diamond way. I'm
teaching you diamond way. Okay. All
right. Next question.
Such a cute people.
Okay,
online.
Malaysians, congratulations on your new
stupa. You Malaysia people
[Applause]
is it okay that I ask this question in
Chinese? Sure.
[Music]
So thank you Gisha for the teaching in
the past two days. It seems like in the
diamond way teaching a lot of what we
have to do is to visualize and for
example we have to visualize ourselves
as mandushri but logically for me that's
not possible because I have trouble
seeing myself as mandushri so what can
we do in a diamond way practice um if
this visualization doesn't work for me
what are the practice that I can do to
bring diamond weight into my life thank
you nice and
Okay.
Uh, one thing that John Brady did in his
database,
uh, so there's I don't know we we are
planning to input 300,000 books. He
is he's about three or 4% finished. It
will take another hundred to 300 years
to finish. Okay, that's how long he has
to stay. Uh, and uh, it's it's huge.
It's unbelievable. It's 300,000 books.
The western classics on which all
western universities are based, there's
500 books. Okay? Harvard
University classics library has 500
books. That's all. Uh, Asia has 300,000
and they are high quality. They're not
silly books. Uh, they're they're not
kunaiforestian. I said Babylonian.
Somebody corrected me. Sumerian. There's
Sumerian. To be honest, I don't know the
difference. But,
um, they're not
some complaint about a guy's horse. They
are extraordinary books. Every one of
them can get you enlightened. 300,000
books, you know,
uh from all the ancient books that you
heard about sutra and chastra yesterday,
right? Uh there's 990 sutras and tantras
left from many thousands and there's
3,700 shastras left. And there's about
285,000 commentaries, late commentaries.
And then
um the ancient people divided the
uh they divided all of those books into
categories. Okay. Uh in the congre
something like that. The whole congre
has only
12 sections.
990 books. The Tenure has something like
sections. Okay. Uh John Brady's database
has probably a
thousand. It's a thousand
different divisions. It's
cataloged correctly and it took many
years. It took 30 years to do it. Uh so
there's about a
thousand categories. Why do I mention
that there's 160 tantras in the
database? Bajuini is one. Mjushi is one.
Amitabal is one. There's there's 160.
John Brady's project has
identified 160 tantras tantric
systems with thousands of books in them,
you know. So it's unbelievable. Then
each one vajogini is divided into many
many categories. The how to do retreat,
how to do the fire, how to do the
mantra, how to do the meditation, how to
do the how to die, you know, how to
teach it, how to do the initiation.
uh many many uh then then
I I asked my teacher you know I said
you're teaching us two or
three tantric traditions you know we get
uh we get
yamant and we get vajugini we get two
basically but there's 160 you know and
and then all my friends who were
studying with other teachers they're
like getting 10, 12,
50. I'm like, we only got
two. I was kind of irritated, you know.
And he said, uh, that's all that I
pract. That's all that we practice in
the tantric monastery. The highest,
there's only two in Tibet. There's
thousands of monastery. There's only two
tantric monasteries. And he's he's like,
"That's all that's all I studied. That's
all we studied. we studied too, you
know. I'm like, "Wow, you know, why is
that?" You know, and he said, I said,
"Why are all those stun? Why they
exist?" And he said, "Everybody's
different." You know, everybody needs a
different teaching. That's why there's
five
houses, right? Everybody's
attracted to a different thing. It's the
Veronica at the cowboy shop story.
You know, she my wife tried on 42 pairs
of
jeans. I counted. I had to stand up the
whole time. There's no
chair. I was irritated. I wanted to go
home. And then she didn't buy any of
them. Don't ever tell her this story.
Uh it means uh different people need
different tantras. Uh there's there's
160 pairs of pants there.
there's 160 uh holy beings, you know,
and probably there's
thousands that survive in John's
database, there's 160, you know, and
u
so you came to this one, you know, and
and then if you tell me, if you tell
your teacher, you know what, I don't
really connect
with
yatka, you know, And I'll be honest, I
don't connect with them either. Okay.
I'm
like, I'm like, it's scary and it's kind
of, you
know, you know, and I'm like, I got any
other choices here? And my teacher's
like, I think you're a
bajogini person. I think you're a
bajgerini type, which is like, you know,
oh my god. you know, and uh so my
teacher's approach, my teacher's
tradition in the ancient tradition,
which is 2,000 years old, uh we give you
basically several
choices. You know, you can have
the tough one if you want, you know, uh
or you can have the sweet angel one. And
personally, I like the sweet angel one.
I I connect with that. So I I when you
study diamond way
uh your teacher should give you a couple
options and basically we give you option
or we give you bajioini option and you
don't need to know about it now you
don't have to worry about it now you
don't have to choose that house
now just sit enjoy the diamond weight
classes uh but the options are waiting
for you we have them okay so if it
doesn't feel like it fits very well
right away. Don't stress about it. You
you will change or the or we'll offer
you a different tantra, a different
tradition. They're all the same in the
end. It's all Lord
Buddha just looking like different pairs
of
pants. It's one person who looks like 42
pairs of pants, 160 pairs of pants. In
the end, it's the same person. Okay. So,
but uh I I
also believe that um as I mentioned
before, you can go with the bajioini
who's more comfortable for you. You feel
more attracted to a feminine Buddha, a
female
Buddha, you know, that's fine. And then
some people want a real authority
figure, president. We know who you know
uh whose name cannot be mean.
Uh you know you can uh you can it
depends on what you feel comfortable
with. And so what's cool about diamond
way
practice basically there's many many
options waiting for you. So if it
doesn't feel like it fits right
away there's two choices.
um go for the other one which fits more
in this tradition. We have other ones if
you like. But I'll tell you another
option. I think I mentioned it the other
day. Uh out of the Gishi
course, there's five great topics.
There's abidharma, ganaya, logic,
uh lower middle way, higher middle way,
and then mind only is in there
somewhere.
And
uh and when I studied the Gishi course,
when I got to the logic, I hated it. I
really hated it. And uh I I was like, I
can't do this. I'm quitting. I'm going
to quit now. You know, it's like I could
care less
about was it major premise, minor
premise? You know, it's all BS to me. I
don't care.
I had real trouble with it and my
teacher at that time couldn't speak
English. So he's like you trouble my
talk. I'm
like I don't understand anything. And
then he tried to explain logic terms in
elementary English and I'm like it's
worth you
know and and I'll tell you something and
I told this story many times. I was uh
walking back to my room from his room
and u he had just given me a logic class
and I was
like and I was sleeping on the floor of
a garage. I was sleeping on a concrete
floor in a sleeping bag. That was my
room. I couldn't I didn't have enough
money or I didn't have any place and uh
there was no place. I'm sleeping on the
floor of a garage with a drunk with an
old drunk who who hid in the garage and
I'm always afraid he's gonna kill me,
you know. And u So anyway, I'm on my way
to my
room. And I remember I stopped under a
tree and I was upset because I said, I
don't know if I can do this. I don't
know if I can learn this, you know. And
then this voice came to me and it said,
"You kick ass on the logic, you know,
you do the logic, okay? It's something
important, something you're supposed to
do, you know, shut up and learn it and
master it, you know, and I and I'm
like, "Wow, I got a message, you know,
and I was I and I in that moment under
the tree, I think you can still see the
tree." I said, "I'm going to do this,
you know. I'm gonna It's the thing I
like. It's the thing I don't like the
most. It's the
one subject I don't like the most." And
I And someow I got a message. It said,
"You're supposed to do the thing you
don't like the most because that's what
you don't have
yet." Got you understand that's the
practice you don't have yet. And so
that's the one you need. you know, the
one that you don't like the most is the
one that's missing inside of you, you
know, and that's a very interesting
idea, you know.
So, I you
can wait and and we'll give you other
traditions. John Brady, Connie, those
guys, they can give you other they will
give you other lineages, other
traditions. There's a lot of
choices. You can wait until something
comes which fits your unusual
bottom.
Okay, you can wait. But you have this
other option that maybe the one you're
not attracted to is a message. Maybe
it's what you are lacking that you need.
Okay? And and so I became good at
logic. I'm I'm the best. Okay. It's
extremely difficult and and I I killed
myself for many years and uh now I know
it and it's wonderful. It's like the
most valuable thing. Okay. So, don't
always think that the thing that's
comfortable for you is the right thing
for
you. Maybe the one that you're not
attracted to is the one that you don't
have. Is that's what that's what you
need. So sometimes in
Buddhism, force yourself to do what you
not attracted
to. If you just keep doing what you're
attracted to, you don't learn anything
new. Okay? Understand? Cool. Don't
forget that one. Okay. All right. How
much time we got,
Tim?
Okay. I'm Who's choosing the Oh, go
ahead. Go ahead. Thank you so much Kesha
for teaching today's yesterday while I
was reading book by uh Lord Jetson Kappa
I sing uh hummingbird in English am I
right
hummingbird it came to me while I was
reading his book oh nice yeah and I was
so happy and I shared this news with my
karmic partner and my roommate Olga and
next day can you imagine she saw
hummingbird as well and I've checked
with AI and AI told me that this is a
sign of of Easy enlightenment. I I
thought that it's h suited for me. Easy
enlightenment. Easy enlightenment. Like
easy easy way to enlightenment. Okay.
Like without suffering. Yeah. Yeah. So I
love it. And my question is so yesterday
I saw like good sign and if I and if we
see like let's say everything comes from
our karma and if for example I see like
bad sign what should I do for powers?
Yeah good. Okay good question. Thank you
so much. All right.
Thank you so much. Yeah I my llama said
something about that. I'm trying to
remember.
Oh, yeah. Okay. Here's the
answer. So, I lived with my llama cuz I
was his driver, his toilet cleaner, his
cook, his
lawnmower, and uh the when you serve a
llama, then you get to hear everything
they say.
So it's a dirty job for 25 years, but
you learn a lot because you're always
with them. So whatever they tell people,
you hear it. So here's what he said one
day to somebody. And uh he said, uh they
said, "Oh,
Rimpuche, you know,
uh sometimes I have these beautiful
signs in dream. I have these wonderful
dreams, you know, and uh I see the sky
opening up and I see Tonkappa coming out
of the sky and and I have these
extraordinary dreams and and uh so I
want to ask you first of all what do
those mean? How do I interpret those
dreams? you know, and then they said,
"And sometimes I have a
nightmare and uh sometimes terrible
things come to me in in the dream and uh
bad bad seems like bad signs, but I
don't know how to read them, you know,
and I want to ask your advice, you know,
and he here's his
answer. In the diamond way, when you
have a beautiful dream and something
amazing happens and you like meet a
Buddha in the dream or you know you're
flying in the dream or you know you
become a female Buddha or something like
that, that's a true
sign that you are making progress. When
the hummingbird comes to you and you
feel like this is a guiding you to
enlightenment,
uh it's a good sign and your practice is
really going well. And he said he said,
"Congratulations." I thought it was
weird to congratulate the person for a
dream, you know. He's like,
"Congratulations." And and and I'm like,
"Yeah." And then the person said, "The
bad dreams and what about the bad
dreams? Bad science." And he said, "You
ate something bad in the
afternoon." Like you ate a old piece of
pizza or uh you know what did you eat,
Rob? I don't remember.
Uh you know, you ate a bad egg or
something, you know. And he
said that's the that's how valid the bad
messages are. And basically he's saying
excuse me, but he's saying her. You
know, if you have a bad message, you
have a bad sign, you know, a cloud goes
over the sun and everything turns dark,
you can say, uh, that I had a bad
lunch. That's all he said. Don't give it
any attention. Don't pay attention to
it. He's like, you just just think I ate
something bad or, you know, something
like that. It's it's just like having
boobs, you know,
boobs. You know, you ate something bad
and you have boobs. It's like a vision.
Bad vision is a boop. And he said just
ignore it. If you're his advice was
uh attached to the great visions and pay
a lot of time spend a lot of time
thinking about them and then when some
some bad sign comes or something just
say don't give them the honor don't give
them respect just say go away you know
I'm I'm not even going to think about
you you know some scorpion comes you're
Okay. Seriously, I like that. I I like
the pizza thing. All right. I think we
got time for one more, Tim. I don't
know.
No. Oh, okay. We have
[Music]
Okay. Okay.
So, we have an online question and it
says, "Hi, Grandpa. You've mentioned I'm
not answered.
You've mentioned in the
past one has to finish geisha course
before learning the diamond way. What is
the seed that allows us now to be able
to learn diamond way without needing to
complete gasha course?
How should we continue to reinvest these
seeds? What was the last question? How
do we continue to reinvest in these
seeds? Reinvest. Reinvest. Okay. Seeds.
Okay. My opinion is uh if you finish the
18 courses and then you do diamond way
and you do the 18 diamond way courses,
your practice will be more firm. And
uh teachers in the world right now of
this thing, teachers of this kind of
thing that we talking about today are
extremely rare. There's not enough.
There's a very bad shortage of teachers.
Uh, I like to say it's like New York.
Imagine New York City or
Singapore with two doctors or something
because that's the way it is. There's
only a few people for every thousand
people who understand these things.
There's only a few people who can teach.
Uh, so all those people are suffering
and there's no doctors. there's a
shortage of doctors, you know, and uh
so in my opinion, we have to uh do what
we have to do to create more doctors as
as as fast as we can safely. I mean, you
don't uh give uh a person two weeks of
training and give them a scalpel and say
do heart surgery, you know. No, you're
going to kill somebody. You're going to
hurt somebody, you know. So there's as
as we don't have much time. Uh you I
don't know how long you're going to
live. I don't know how long I'm going to
live. You we don't know who will die
first. We have to get it done now. We
have to take care of it now. So I I
would say
um start the start you there will be
requirements Tim can tell you for ACI
people to learn Diamond Way to teach
Diamond Way. There are requirements.
It's better if you can do the 18
courses. It's better if you can do the
18 Diamond Way courses. It's better. You
will be a better doctor.
everything. There's an old kind of
doctor called general practitioner GP. I
have one. They're very rare. Uh she's a
female GP. She's about my age. And they
stop making them. They don't make them
anymore. You know, you you go to a
doctor and and they they say, "How
what's wrong?" You say, "I got a
headache." Oh, you got to go to a
headache specialist. And they send you
to another doctor. you know, and then
you say, "I got something with my toe."
And, "Oh, you got to go to a toe
specialist, you know, and it's a lot of
money also, by the way." And they keep
sending you to specialist. It's very
rare to find someone who who's an old
old-fashioned GP, general practitioner,
general doctor who knows who knows all
the different problems pretty well, you
know, and so I would like to create GPS.
I I would like ACI to create GPS. Uh I
would like you to master many things,
many subjects. Then when someone asks
you a question about bad dreams or or
bad
hummingbirds, you're you have an answer
ready for them. You don't have to say,
"Oh, go talk
to Sophie in in Tokyo." You know, I
don't know the answer. You see what I
mean? It's better if you can learn a
lot. So I think as a doctor, the best
doctors I know, they never stop
studying. They even they're 60 years
old, 70 years old. You say, "Can I can I
see you next week?" They say, "No." And
you say, "Why?" And they say, "I'm
taking a class." And I'm like, "You're
60, 70 years old. Why are you taking a
class?" I want to learn more. I want to
I want to be able to help more people. I
I respect that kind of doctor that then
that kind of doctor, they're always
learning the new techniques. And you
know, my wife had a a knee surgery. We
got knee knee
replacement. And uh this guy has a new
what do you call it? He does the
operation with a
robot. Okay. So there's 20 doctors who
can do it with their
hands and and there's one who can do it
with a robot and the robot is much more
precise and you heal faster. And then
she was now she's fine. You can't tell
which knee is operation. She's both
knees are wonderful, you know. So this
person, he's already a a great surgeon.
He's already very famous. Uh he can cut
you up very well. Uh but he went on to
learn the robot. He wanted to learn the
robot also. And now he has the choice.
Some difficult operation needs a hands
and most of them are fine with the
robot. And the robot is more precise and
it doesn't make mistakes like human
beings make. And uh I think it's good to
know. I like the surgeon. I like to go
to the surgeon who knows both and then
then I get I can get which one is better
for me. You see I mean so I think as a
teacher
u I don't want you to come to me and say
should I take 14 courses or 15
courses you know I say take all of them
and then take them again and then take
them a third time you know don't ask me
this
irritating
question you know if I do 13 and a half
can I teach you know and I don't ask me
to make those decisions you
learn the robot and learn to do it by
hand. And and as soon as you can help
somebody, start helping them. You don't
have to wait till you've mastered the
robot. You know, you can you can help
people, you know, don't hurt people. You
know, if you hand a steak knife to a kid
and say, "Do a heart operation." I'm
like, you know, I think I'll wait a
while. you know, so it's a delicate
question. We want people who don't hurt
other people,
uh, who don't make mistakes teaching
people, and we want but we don't want to
wait until you've had 50 years of
experience because then you can only
help a few people. So, it's kind of your
the the answer. I stick with whatever
Tim says, first of all, and then
secondly, uh, you can't stop learning. I
mean you should never stop learning
this. You can you can study diamond way
for hundred lifetimes. You will not
master it. There's it's endless. Okay.
But you you have to as as soon as you
can do the hard work to learn as much as
you can and then you can help more
people. Okay. And and if you want to
know the how many courses blah blah talk
to Tim.
Okay. Thank you.
[Applause]
Um, and if if it's me and if John Brady,
Connie, Ellie, those guys are giving
courses. I know Peter and Maria are
teaching Diamond Way. If it's me, I'll
I'll try to go to all of
them. Okay.